Rowan Christie

Former initials S. C.

Email: smc9227@rit.edu
Github account: https://github.com/SMCCoder

Phone: 541-736-6763

I am an undergraduate student at RIT studying bioinformatics and ecoinformatics. I have learned various skills such as R, python, and ArcGIS during the course of my study. I hope to learn more about interdisciplinary approaches utilizing software tools in my future research.

EDUCATION

BS in Bioinformatics, Rochester Institute of Technology expected 2021 High School Diploma, Academy of Arts and Academics 2017

GRANTS & FELLOWSHIPS

NTID/RIT RISE fellowship

2018 - 2021

The Research Initiative for Scientific Enhancement is a PhD prep program for Deaf and Hard of Hearing undergraduates in science. Two scholars are selected each year to conduct research with a mentor for three years, participate in specialized research courses, and receive professional development training.

RIT COS HHMI Inclusive Excellence fellowship

2018

The HHMI Inclusive Excellence fellowship is a summer research program which aims to provide students from nontraditional pathways opportunities in STEM research and develop an inclusive environment within this field.

HONORS & AWARDS

David M. Baldwin Memorial Scholarship	2020
Special Interest Housing Community Service Person of the Year Award	2019
RIT Dean's List Fall 2017-2019, Spring 2018-2019	2017 - 2019
Joseph C. and Loretta F. Wolf Scholarship	2018
NTID Presidential Scholarship	2018
NTID Academic Excellence Scholarship	2018

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Scholar, Rochester NY

8/27/2018-present

Rochester Institute of Technology Research Initiative for Scientific Enhancement

With Dr. Kaitlin Stack Whitney, I continued my independent research, creating spatial and GIS models focusing on freshwater macroinvertebrates. Additionally, I started a new project with collaborators from Kent State University, focusing on temporal analyses on long term *Ixodes scapularis* (tick) abundance data.

Research Fellow, Rochester NY

5/28/2018-8/3/2018

2018 RIT HHMI Inclusive Excellence Summer Research Fellowship Program With Dr. Kaitlin Stack Whitney, I developed an independent research project examining how freshwater macroinvertebrates respond to environmental variables in the US using ecoinformatics approaches and R statistical software.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

S. Christie, K. Whitney. Invited panelist for "Working Together: Establishing Productive Training Environments with Hearing Mentors and D/HH Trainees in Science." Deaf-Engaged Academic Forum (DEAF ROC) at the University of Rochester. Rochester NY, August 2019.

CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Comparing Stability Trends in Long Term Deer Tick Population Datasets." Poster for Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students. Anaheim, CA. November 2019.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.10269734.v2

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Comparing Stability Trends in Long Term Deer Tick Population Datasets." Poster for 46th Annual Rochester Academy of Sciences Fall Scientific Paper Session. Rochester, NY. November 2019.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.10269734.v2

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Ixodes scapularis (Lyme disease vector) population interannual stability trends in long term datasets". Poster for Deaf-Engaged Academic Forum (DEAF ROC). Rochester, NY. August 2019.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.9461405.v1

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Ixodes scapularis (Lyme disease vector) population interannual stability trends in long term datasets." Oral presentation for RIT Undergraduate Research Symposium. Rochester, NY. August 2019.

 $\underline{https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.9461453.v1}$

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Modeling Macroinvertebrate Communities and Ecological Health." Poster for NTID Research Fair. Rochester, NY. April 2019.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8800967.v1

- S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Modeling Macroinvertebrate Communities and Ecological Health." Oral presentation for Research Spotlights: Health and Life Sciences. Rochester, NY. April 2019. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8637011.v1
- S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Modeling Macroinvertebrate Communities and Ecological Health." Poster for Entomology Society of America. Vancouver, British Columbia. November 2018. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8812850.v1
- S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Modeling Macroinvertebrate Communities and Ecological Health." Oral presentation for 45th Annual Rochester Academy of Sciences Fall Scientific Paper Session. Geneseo, NY. November 2018.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8812922.v1

S. Christie, K. Whitney. "Modeling US freshwater macroinvertebrate communities and ecological health." Poster for RIT Undergraduate Research Symposium. Rochester, NY, August 2018.

https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8813051.v1

SERVICE

Project Manager, RIT House of General Science

2018-2019

Elected project manager of a Special Interest House for RIT dorm students with an interest in any field of science. Managed and guided 7 project teams to present at ImagineRIT and coordinated school outreach events. I also frequently participate in social and community service events.

Member, RIT Fowl Play

2018-2019

An entertainment troupe dedicated to comedy. I regularly participate in skits and improv games. Performed in 3 shows.

Tech Head, RIT House of General Science

2017

Elected Tech Head of a Special Interest House for RIT dorm students with an interest in any field of science. Improved the website, set up a server, and maintained the groupchat.

OUTREACH

Volunteer, National Chemistry Week at the Rochester Museum and Science Center. October 2019.

Helped present inorganic metal-based chemistry activities to the public at a chemistry event hosted by the RMSC.

Volunteer coordinator, House of General Science at K-12 Campus Visits. October 2019. Coordinated two activities involving fruit batteries and structures with skewers and clay for groups of elementary and middle school aged kids visiting RIT to learn about science.

Exhibitor, House of General Science at ImagineRIT. April 2019.

As the head of the project, created a wooden Rube Goldberg Machine to demonstrate the law of conservation of energy for the annual innovation festival at RIT.

Volunteer coordinator, House of General Science at STEAM Day at Jefferson Road Elementary School. April 2019

Coordinated a demonstration creating homemade Lava Lamps to present to elementary-aged kids.

Exhibitor, House of General Science at ImagineRIT. April 2018.

Helped create a gloved device that can play different instruments for each finger when tapped on a conductive piece of metal for the annual innovation festival at RIT.

SKILLS

Coding languages
R, python, Java, C++, Javascript

Relevant coursework

Bioinformatics (Fall 2019), Evolutionary Biology (Fall 2019), Organic Chemistry 1 (Fall 2019), Advanced GIS (Spring 2019), Genetics (Spring 2019), Intro to GIS (Fall 2018), Cellular and Molecular Biology (Fall 2018), Fundamentals of Bioinformatics (Spring 2017), Introduction to Statistics I (Spring 2018)

REFERENCES

Dr. Kaitlin Stack Whitney, kxwsbi@rit.edu

Dr. Karl Korfmacher, kfkscl@rit.edu